Finding aid for the Collection of Cuban Slavery Documents LSC.2335
UCLA Library Special Collections
Collection of Cuban slavery documents
circa 1816-1890s
UCLA Library Special Collections
LSC.2335
0.4 linear feet (1 box)
The forced enslavement of individuals in Cuba began in the early 1500s and continued until 1886. Spanish colonists first enslaved Cuba's indigenous population, and then began forcibly transporting individuals from Africa in the late 1700s as Cuba's sugar industry, which relied heavily on enslaved labor, increased. Throughout the 1800s, amongst international pressure to cease the Atlantic slave trade, Spanish colonists and Cuban plantation owners sought out other systems of forced labor. Cuba did not cease its involvement in the Atlantic slave trade until 1867 and slavery was not officially abolished until 1886. The Collection of Cuban slavery documents ranges from circa 1816-1890s and contains death certificates, labor contracts, identification documents (cédula), enslaved bills of sale, relocation permits, two sets describing emancipation cases, legal documents, correspondence, and governmental reports. Sources: "A fifteen part archive of documents relating to Cuban slavery: labor, administration, runaways, and emancipation." Description by Libros Latinos, February 19, 2016. Hu-Dehart, Evelyn. "Chinese Coolie Labor in Cuba in the Nineteenth Century: Free Labor of Neoslavery." Contributions in Black Studies: A Journal of African and Afro-American Studies 12, article 5 (1994): 38-54. https://scholarworks.umass.edu/cibs/vol12/iss1/5. Scott, Rebecca. Slave Emancipation In Cuba: The Transition to Free Labor, 1860–1899. Pittsburgh: University of Pittsburgh Press, 2000. Tan, Hai Lun. "Monuments of a Hidden Past: Deconstructing the Historical Narrative of the Chinese in Cuba, 1847-1959." Honors thesis, Wesleyan University, 2018. https://doi.org/10.14418/wes01.1.1474.
Conditions Governing Access
Open for research. All requests to access special collections materials must be made in advance using the request button located on this page.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Purchased from Libros Latinos, 2016.
UCLA Catalog Record ID
UCLA Catalog Record ID: 9993613113606533
Biographical / Historical
The forced enslavement of individuals in Cuba began in the early 1500s and continued until 1886. Spanish colonists first enslaved Cuba's indigenous population, and then began forcibly transporting individuals from Africa in the late 1700s as Cuba's sugar industry, which relied heavily on enslaved labor, increased. Throughout the 1800s, amongst international pressure to cease the Atlantic slave trade, Spanish colonists and Cuban plantation owners sought out other systems of forced labor. These systems essentially continued the same practices and conditions of enslavement but were disguised as contract labor. This included a system in China, where individuals were forcibly, deceptively, and coercively recruited into signing labor contracts and then subsequently transported to Cuba. A system known as patronato also became common. Former enslavers, known as patronos, contracted formerly enslaved individuals, known as patrocinados, into an eight year period of labor, often at the same locations where they had previously worked in bondage. Cuba did not cease its involvement in the Atlantic slave trade until 1867 and slavery was not officially abolished until 1886.
Sources:
Hu-Dehart, Evelyn. "Chinese Coolie Labor in Cuba in the Nineteenth Century: Free Labor of Neoslavery." Contributions in Black Studies: A Journal of African and Afro-American Studies 12, article 5 (1994): 38-54. https://scholarworks.umass.edu/cibs/vol12/iss1/5.
Scott, Rebecca. Slave Emancipation In Cuba: The Transition to Free Labor, 1860–1899. Pittsburgh: University of Pittsburgh Press, 2000.
Tan, Hai Lun. "Monuments of a Hidden Past: Deconstructing the Historical Narrative of the Chinese in Cuba, 1847-1959." Honors thesis, Wesleyan University, 2018. https://doi.org/10.14418/wes01.1.1474.
Scope and Content
The collection of Cuban slavery documents range from circa 1816-1890s and contains death certificates, labor contracts, identification documents (cédula), enslaved bills of sale, relocation permits, two sets of documents describing emancipation cases, legal documents, correspondence, and governmental reports.
"A fifteen part archive of documents relating to Cuban slavery: labor, administration, runaways, and emancipation." Description by Libros Latinos, February 19, 2016.
Arrangement
This collection is arranged according to the existing order in which it was received.
Slavery -- Cuba; Indentured servants; Contract labor
- Death certificates, circa 1870s-1890s (Box 1, Folder 1)
  Scope and Contents
  This folder contains 140 documents including death certificates issued for enslaved and emancipated Afro-Cubans.
- Death certificates, circa 1870s (Box 1, Folder 2)
  This folder contains 190 documents including death certificates issued for Chinese and Asian individuals.
- Labor contracts, 1868 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  This folder contains five labor contracts issued in Cuba to Chinese individuals.
- Identification documents and enslaved bills of sale, circa 1860s (Box 1, Folder 4)
  This folder contains five documents issued in Cuba to Chinese individuals.
- Identification documents, circa 1850s (Box 1, Folder 5)
  This folder contains five documents issued to emancipated people of color.
- Enslaved bills of sale, emancipation, circa 1850s (Box 1, Folder 6)
- Relocation permits, circa 1840s (Box 1, Folder 7)
  This folder contains four documents issued to emancipated individuals.
- Emancipation set, 1884 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  This folder contains documents concerning a Black enslaved individual named Simon seeking emancipation from his enslaver, Julian Gomez.
- Emancipation set, 1880 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  This folder contains thirteen pages of text concerning an enslaved woman's emancipation.
- Legal deposits, 1885 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  This folder contains two documents concerning pending cases to be heard by the Provincial Board of Sponsored People.
- Letter, 1848 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  This folder contains a three page letter concerning self-emancipated individuals.
- Governor request, 1838 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  This folder contains four documents totaling six pages, including a request by the governor concerning self-emancipated individuals.
- Report, 1830 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  This folder contains a five page report concerning self-emancipated individuals.
- Correspondence, 1822 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  This folder contains seven documents totaling ten pages, including official and mayoral correspondence concerning the stolen labor of enslaved individuals to complete construction of the port of Monserrate.
- Documents, 1816 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  This folder contains two documents concerning the suspension of the slave trade.